They fought south of the city, and died north of the wall.
قاتلوا جنوب المدينة وسقطوا قتلى شمال الأسوار
[Yongzhou]
[يونغتشو]
Left out in the wild, unburied, for the crows to peck and gnaw.
ماتوا في البرية دون دفن، لتأكلهم الغربان
Tell the crows for me: eat well, feast your fill.
قولوا للغربان من أجلي: لا تتعجّلوا في التهامهم، بل عاملوهم كأنهم ضيوف
Left in the wild, surely unburied— how could rotten flesh escape your beak?
فمن مات في البرية لن يجد من يدفنه وكيف لجسدٍ بدأ يتحلل أن ينهض هاربًا منكم؟
Well, Xiao Wuyi...
شياو وو يي، يا شياو وو يي
After all these years of war,
لقد خضت الحروب لسنوات عديدة
you still haven't earned a good reputation.
ولم تترك سمعة طيبة
[Yang Yi's Mansion, Armory Director]
[قصر يانغ يي، أمين مستودع الأسلحة]
[Li Mao, Prince of Qi, styled Yizhi]
[أمير تشي، لي ماو، واسمه الأدبي يي تشي]
This family
هذه العائلة
seems to have been gone for a long time.
يبدو أنهم رحلوا منذ زمن طويل
Da.
آ دا
Everyone is gone.
لقد اختفى الجميع
How am I supposed to look into this?
كيف لي أن أحقق في الأمر؟
[Da, guard to the Prince of Qi]
[حارس أمير تشي، آ دا]
I need to tell Wuyi about all this.
يجب أن أبلغ وو يي بهذا
[Key to the Phoenix Heart]
[مفتاح قلب العنقاء]
[Episode 3]
[الحلقة الثالثة]
Yizhi!
يي تشي
Wuyi.
وو يي
What are you doing here?
ما الذي أتى بك إلى هنا؟
I was waiting for you.
أنا هنا في انتظارك
Xiao Wuyi!
شياو وو يي
How did you know I was coming back to the capital today?
كيف علمت أنني سأعود إلى العاصمة اليوم؟
In your letter, you said you were coming back by water.
ذكرت في رسالتك أنك ستعود إلى العاصمة عبر الطريق المائي
Counting the days, it had to be today,
وبحساب الأيام، توقعت أن تصل اليوم
so I came here to wait for you.
لذا انتظرتك هنا خصيصًا
I heard the battle at Jiuzhang Plain was especially brutal.
سمعت أن معركة سهل جيوتشانغ كانت شرسة للغاية
How are you?
كيف حالك؟
Let me have a look at you.
دعني ألقي نظرة عليك
I'm fine.
أنا بخير
You've been traveling day and night this whole way.
لقد عانيت من مشقة السفر طوال الطريق
You must be starving.
فلا بد أنك جوعان
I brought your favorite taro pastries.
جلبتُ لك معجنات القلقاس المفضلة لديك
Hurry and try some.
هيا تذوقها
You really know me.
أنت أكثر من يفهمني يا أخي
I've been sick of dry rations this entire journey.
لقد سئمت من تناول الطعام الجاف طوال الطريق
I've been saving my appetite for getting back to Jiankang.
كنت أوفر شهيتي حتى أعود إلى جيانكانغ
Watch your manners.
انتبه لصورتك قليلًا
Look at you, eating like a starving ghost.
انظر إلى نفسك، تبدو كشبح جائع
How are you supposed to be the elegant Prince Qi from the rumors?
لا تشبه أبدًا أمير تشي الأنيق الذي يتحدث عنه الجميع
That's a bad habit from back when we were on the run.
هذه عادة سيئة اكتسبتها عندما كنت أهرب في الماضي
If you eat too slowly,
إذا أكلت ببطء
your food gets snatched and you starve.
فسيُسرق طعامي وسأموت جوعًا
I still haven't managed to shake it.
لم أستطع التخلص منها حتى الآن
Yizhi,
يي تشي
thank you for helping with the matter in Yongzhou.
شكرًا لك على مساعدتك في شأن يونغتشو
Wuyi,
وو يي
is something wrong?
هل هناك أمر ما؟
I waited here for you today
انتظرتك هنا خصيصًا اليوم
because I want you to stay out of the capital for now.
لأطلب منك عدم العودة إلى العاصمة في الوقت الحالي
Something is about to happen in the capital.
هناك كارثة على وشك الحدوث في العاصمة
Don't tell me it's Prince Changsha again.
لا تقل لي إنه أمير تشانغشا
No.
لا
It's me.
بل أنا
What did you do?
ما مشكلتك؟
I'm taking a secondary consort.
سأتزوج محظية
Again?
!ستتزوج مجددًا
Isn't that a good thing?
أليس هذا أمرًا جيدًا؟
I'll be your best man.
سأكون إشبينك
This marriage was arranged by the Empress Dowager.
هذا الزواج أمرت به الإمبراطورة الأرملة
The whole city is bound to be watching.
لذا من المحتم أن يجذب انتباه المدينة بأكملها
And Prince Changsha has been planning for this for a long time.
وأمير تشانغشا يخطط منذ فترة طويلة
There's no way he'll willingly let me marry this lady.
ولن يرضى أبدًا بزواجي من هذه الفتاة
When the time comes,
عندما يحين الوقت
chaos is bound to break out in the capital,
ستعم الفوضى بين جميع الأطراف في العاصمة
and bloodshed will be inevitable.
ولا مفر من مذبحة دامية
It will be safest for you to return
انتظر حتى يهدأ كل شيء ثم عُد
only after everything has settled.
سيكون ذلك أكثر أمانًا
Now I'm curious.
لقد أثرت فضولي
Just which family's daughter
من هي هذه الفتاة
has both you and Prince Changsha fighting to marry her?
التي تتنافسان أنت وأمير تشانغشا على الزواج منها؟
The daughter of Grand Tutor Xie—
ابنة المعلم الأكبر شيه
Xie Jiayu.
شيه جيا يوي
Prince Qi is back!
لقد عاد سمو أمير تشي
It's been more than half a year. You finally made it back.
لقد مر أكثر من نصف عام، وأخيرًا عدت
Master has really missed you.
لقد اشتاق إليك المعلم كثيرًا
Come on, let's go drink now that you're back.
بما أنك عدت، فلنذهب للشرب
Alright, alright.
حسنًا، حسنًا
Master.
يا معلمي
You should all head back first.
عودوا أنتم أولًا
Head back first.
عودوا أولًا
Master, I heard—
...يا معلمي، سمعت أن
I already know.
أنا أعلم
I remember you once told me
أتذكر أنك قلت ذات مرة
that during the unrest in Qizhou,
إنه أثناء تمرد تشيتشو في ذلك العام
you ran into danger on your way back to the capital.
واجهت خطرًا في طريق عودتك إلى العاصمة
It was Young Master Xiao who saved you and escorted you
وأنقذك ولي العهد شياو
and the Princess of Pingning County safely back to the capital.
ورافقك أنت وأميرة بينغنينغ في العودة إلى العاصمة
You've known each other since then?
أنتما... تعرفان بعضكما منذ زمن طويل
Yes.
نعم
Have you been in contact recently?
هل تواصلتما مؤخرًا؟
It is a friendship of gentlemen.
صداقتنا نبيلة
So in your eyes,
في قلبك
Young Master Xiao is actually a gentleman?
ولي العهد شياو رجل نبيل؟
When we were young, he once told me
عندما كان صغيرًا، قال لي
that, for the sake of protecting the realm,
إنه من أجل حماية العالم
he wanted
في هذه الحياة
to become the greatest general under heaven.
سيكون أعظم قائد في العالم
But after returning to the capital,
ولكن بعد عودته إلى العاصمة
he killed court officials and intimidated the entire court.
قتل وزراء البلاط وأرهب المسؤولين
Do you still think
هل تعتقد أنه لا يزال
he's the same young man you once knew?
ذلك الشاب الذي عرفته في الماضي؟
"How shall it be said that you have no clothes?
"أيُقال لا ثوبَ لنا؟" "اسم وو يي يعني بلا ثياب"
I will share my long robes with you."
"معك أرتدي الرداءَ ذاته"
It is his name,
هذا اسمه
and also his aspiration.
ومبدأ حياته أيضًا
Yes.
نعم
Perhaps when Xiao Sheng chose the name "Wuyi"—"No Clothes" — for himself,
ربما عندما اختار شياو شنغ اسم وو يي لنفسه
he truly meant those words.
كان ذلك نابعًا من قلبه حقًا
But power...
لكنها السلطة
Power changes people.
السلطة تغير الإنسان
Perhaps he is no longer
ربما لم يعد
the person you once knew.
الشخص الذي عرفته في البداية
I'll go see him myself.
سأذهب لأبحث عنه
I'll tell him that I like Yao Yao,
سأخبره أنني معجب بجيا يوي
and ask him to call off the marriage.
وأطلب منه إلغاء هذا الزواج
The Empress Dowager herself arranged this marriage.
هذا زواج أمرت به الإمبراطورة الأرملة
How could it possibly be withdrawn?
فكيف يمكن التراجع عنه؟
Then I'll go beg the Empress Dowager.
إذًا سأذهب وأتوسل إلى الإمبراطورة الأرملة
Jiankang Palace is not somewhere you can simply barge into.
ليس من السهل اقتحام قصر جيانكانغ
I know.
أنا أعلم
Master,
يا معلمي
before I returned this time,
في رحلة عودتي هذه
I prepared a betrothal gift for Yao Yao.
أعددت هدية لطلب يد جيا يوي
Please help me pass it on to her.
أرجو منك مساعدتي في تسليمها لها
I've already made up my mind.
لقد قررت بالفعل
No matter how difficult it is,
مهما كانت الصعوبات
even if it means going into Jiankang Palace,
حتى لو كان قصر جيانكانغ
I'm willing to try.
أنا على استعداد للمحاولة
For Yao Yao,
من أجل جيا يوي
I'd do anything.
أنا مستعد لفعل أي شيء
[Grand Tutor's Mansion]
‫‪]‬قصر المعلم الأكبر]‬‬
Mao brought this for you.
هذا ما أحضره لكِ لي ماو
It's black iridescent ore.
إنه حجر وو تساي
In her last letter, Yao Yao mentioned
في المرة الماضية، ذكرت جيا يوي في رسالتها
that Yongzhou produces a rare kind of black iridescent ore
أن مقاطعة يونغتشو تنتج حجر وو تساي النادر جدًا
that can forge the toughest black iron.
والذي يمكن استخدامه لصنع أقوى أنواع الحديد الأسود
Since I'm already there,
وبما أنني أتيت إلى هنا
I'll look for some on her behalf.
قررت أن أبحث عنه من أجلها
It'll make an auspicious gift when I ask for her hand in marriage.
وسيكون هدية مباركة لطلب يدها
I only mentioned it once,
لقد ذكرت ذلك مرة واحدة فقط
and Mao went out of his way to find it for me.
وقد بحث عنه ماو خصيصًا من أجلي
Yao Yao,
جيا يوي
Mao has entered the palace.
لقد دخل ماو القصر
He wants to ask the Empress Dowager
يريد التوسل إلى الإمبراطورة الأرملة
to revoke the imperial marriage decree.
للتراجع عن مرسوم الزواج
I knew it.
كنت أعلم
Mao would never give up.
ماو لن يستسلم أبدًا
You want me to revoke the imperial marriage decree?
تريد مني أن أتراجع عن مرسوم الزواج؟
I humbly ask that Your Majesty grant us your blessing.
أتوسل إلى جلالتكِ أن توافقي
Young men are naturally drawn to beauty.
الإعجاب في سن الشباب
I understand that.
أنا أتفهمه
But
لكن
the decree has already been issued.
المرسوم الإمبراطوري قد صدر بالفعل
I beg Your Majesty for mercy.
يا صاحبة الجلالة، أرجوكِ ارحميني
In this life, I ask for nothing else
ليس لي مطلبٌ آخر في هذه الحياة
but Lady Xie alone.
سوى الزواج من السيدة شيه
You ask for nothing else?
!ليس لك مطلبٌ آخر
Your Majesty once promised
جلالتكِ وعدتِني من قبل
that if I could find a miraculous doctor for His Majesty,
بأنه طالما وجدتُ الطبيب المعجزة لجلالة الإمبراطور
you would grant me another fiefdom.
فسوف تمنحينني إقطاعية أخرى
After enduring countless hardships,
لقد مررتُ بالعديد من الصعاب
I finally succeeded.
ونجحتُ في النهاية
But now, I can forgo
ولكن الآن، الإقطاعية واللقب والثروة
the land, the title, and the wealth.
يمكنني التخلي عنها جميعًا
I ask only that Your Majesty take pity on my sincere feelings.
أتوسل إلى جلالتكِ أن تشفقي على قلبي المخلص
You can give up
الإقطاعية
your land,
واللقب
your title,
والثروة
and your wealth?
يمكنك التخلي عنها جميعًا
It seems
يبدو أنني
I've played the part of a gentle and virtuous woman
مثلتُ دور المرأة اللطيفة لفترة طويلة
for so long that some fools have actually started to believe it.
لدرجة أن بعض الحمقى صدقوا ذلك حقًا
My son sits upon the throne,
ابني على العرش
yet even he struggles just to survive,
يكافح من أجل البقاء
living like a puppet.
ويعيش كدمية
And what are you?
فمن تظن نفسك؟
What is your sincerity worth?
وما قيمة قلبك المخلص هذا؟
How dare you come here and bargain with me?
أتجرؤ على المجيء ومساومتي؟
Everything you have now
كل ما تملكه الآن
was bestowed upon you by His Majesty and me.
هو منحة مني ومن جلالة الإمبراطور
If I decide not to give it,
إذا لم أرغب في العطاء
then you shall have nothing.
فيمكنني ألا أعطي
He Tian!
خه تيان
Your servant awaits.
خادمك في خدمتك
Prince Qi trespassed into the inner palace
أمير تشي اقتحم القصر المحظور
and spoke insolently to the Empress Dowager.
وأهان الإمبراطورة الأرملة
Punish him with the rod!
اجلدوه
Da.
آ دا
It's nothing. What happened?
أنا بخير، ماذا حدث؟
Lejun?
له جيون
Fainted?
أُغمي عليها
Princess.
سمو الأميرة
As soon as Lejun passed out,
بمجرد أن أغمي على له جيون
her maids came straight to the Grand Tutor's residence to fetch me.
جاءت الخادمات إلى قصر المعلم الأكبر لدعوتي
What happened to her?
ماذا حدث لها؟
Don't tell me her old illness has flared up again?
هل يمكن أن يكون مرضها القديم قد عاودها؟
She'll be fine.
إنها بخير
She's fine?
!بخير
What,
ماذا؟
Your Highness doesn't believe me?
ألا تصدقني يا سمو الأمير؟
I wouldn't dare.
لا أجرؤ على ذلك
Your Highness is highly skilled in medicine,
سمو الأميرة بارعة في الطب
and it was you who cured Lejun's chronic illness before.
ومرض له جيون القديم قد عالجتِه سموكِ أيضًا
However,
ولكن
if she is truly fine,
إذا كانت بخير حقًا
then why did she suddenly faint?
فلماذا أغمي عليها؟
She merely ate some wild fruit by mistake.
لقد أكلت بعض الفواكه البرية عن طريق الخطأ
She'll recover naturally in a few days.
وستتحسن بشكل طبيعي في غضون أيام قليلة
However...
...ولكن
something about this is strange.
هذا الأمر غريب
To fall unconscious
تناول الفاكهة البرية
from eating that fruit,
حتى فقد الوعي
one would have to eat at least an entire basketful.
يعني أنها تناولت سلة كاملة على الأقل
The fruit is sour and bitter—
طعم هذه الفاكهة حامض ومر
difficult to swallow.
ومن الصعب تناولها
Why would Lejun eat so much of it?
فكيف يمكن لها أن تأكل كل هذا؟
Go check whether the medicine is ready yet.
اذهبي وتحققي مما إذا كان الدواء قد نضج
Yes.
!أمرك
I'll go check on the medicine as well.
سأذهب لأرى الدواء أيضًا
Yao Yao.
جيا يوي
Mao.
ماو
My mother wouldn't let me leave the residence,
أمي لم تسمح لي بمغادرة القصر
and I wanted to see you.
أردت أن أراك
Lejun said she had a way—
قالت له جيون إن لديها طريقة
I didn't expect this to be what she meant.
لم أتوقع أن تكون هذه هي الطريقة
Are you alright?
هل أنتِ بخير؟
Mao, you're finally back.
ماو، لقد عدت أخيرًا
I thought
ظننت أنني
I was really going to end up marrying someone else.
سأتزوج شخصًا آخر حقًا
The Empress Dowager
الإمبراطورة الأرملة
still refuses to withdraw the decree.
ما زالت ترفض التراجع عن أمرها
Then I won't marry him either.
إذًا لن أتزوج
You're going to defy the imperial decree?
هل ستعصينها؟
Mao,
ماو
I dare to defy the decree.
أنا أجرؤ على عصيانها
Do you dare?
هل تجرؤ أنت؟
Why wouldn't I dare?
ولماذا لا أجرؤ؟
Father always says I know nothing about court politics.
أبي يقول دائمًا إنني لا أفهم في شؤون البلاط
Maybe he's right.
لا أفهم في الأمور الأخرى
But I do know
لكنني أعلم أن أبي
he has no intention of siding with Prince Jingan.
لا يريد اللجوء إلى قصر أمير جينغآن
And besides, the Empress Dowager only ordered me to marry Xiao Wuyi.
علاوة على ذلك، الإمبراطورة الأرملة أمرتني فقط بالزواج من شياو وو يي
She never said I had to spend my life in loving harmony with him.
ولم تقل إن عليّ أن أعيش معه في حب ووئام حتى نشيب
So as long as I complete the ceremony on the wedding night
لذلك، يكفي أن أهرب في ليلة الزفاف
and run away afterward,
بعد إتمام المراسم
it won't count
حينها
as defying the decree.
لن أُعتبر عاصية
I plan to go to Northern Qin,
أما أنا، فأخطط للذهاب إلى تشين الشمالية
change my name,
لأخفي هويتي
and start over.
وأبدأ من جديد
Alright.
حسنًا
Yao Yao,
جيا يوي
no matter how powerful the Emperor and the Empress Dowager are,
مهما كانت سلطة الإمبراطور والإمبراطورة الأرملة واسعة
there's no way they can reach into Northern Qin to arrest anyone.
من المستحيل أن تصل إلى تشين الشمالية للقبض على أحد
It's just that
لكن
the road ahead will be fraught with danger—
هذا الطريق سيكون محفوفًا بالمخاطر حتمًا
you must think this through carefully.
يجب أن تفكري جيدًا
To be honest,
بصراحة
I am a little afraid.
أنا خائفة بعض الشيء
The world outside
هذا العالم الخارجي
is full of killing,
مليء بالقتل
deceit, and betrayal.
والخداع والخيانة
But I can't let fear condemn me
لكن لا يمكنني بسبب الخوف
to spending the rest of my life
أن أُدفن بقية حياتي
trapped in Jingan Mansion.
في قصر أمير جينغآن
Yao Yao,
جيا يوي
no matter how disastrous this may become,
مهما كانت الكارثة كبيرة
if you want to go through with it,
طالما أردتِ خوضها
I'll be with you every step of the way.
سأكون معكِ
What about Lejun?
وماذا عن الأخت له جيون؟
What will happen to her?
ماذا سيحل بها؟
Of course she's coming with us.
بالطبع ستأتي معنا
Don't worry—
اطمئني
she likes you
هي تحبك
far more than she likes me, her own brother.
أكثر بكثير مني، أنا أخوها
Besides,
علاوة على ذلك، لقد اتفقنا آنذاك
back when we were fleeing for our lives,
عندما كنا نهرب
we already promised that we'd face life and death together.
أننا سنبقى معًا في الحياة والموت
Wait here a moment.
انتظرني لحظة
What's this?
ما هذا؟
This...
هذا
can be our token of promise.
ليكن عربون اتفاقنا
I didn't expect things would still be
لم أتوقع أنه مع اقتراب الزفاف
so lively and carefree at Wuyi's place with the wedding so close at hand.
لا يزال مكان وو يي يعج بالغناء والرقص
Is this for your cousin?
هذه هدية لي؟
Don't touch it.
لا تلمسها
Mao, coming by this late at night...
ماو، لقد أتيت في وقت متأخر
you must have something important to say.
لا بد أن لديك أمرًا مهمًا لتقوله، أليس كذلك؟
I assume you've already guessed it.
أعتقد أنك خمنت بالفعل
Lady Xie is the woman I love.
أن السيدة شيه هي حبيبتي
Is that all?
أهذا كل شيء؟
She loves me too.
وهي أيضًا تبادلني المشاعر
A gifted man and a beautiful woman—
شاب موهوب وفتاة جميلة
you are indeed well matched.
بالفعل ثنائي مناسب
I hope you will call off this engagement.
آمل أن تتمكن من فسخ هذا الزواج
And if I refuse?
ولكن ماذا لو لم أرغب في ذلك؟
You pressured the Empress Dowager into issuing the marriage decree
أنت أجبرت الإمبراطورة الأرملة على إصدار مرسوم الزواج
for no reason other than to disrupt Prince Changsha's plans.
ليس إلا لتعطيل مخططات أمير تشانغشا
But Xie Jiayu is a person.
لكن شيه جيا يوي إنسانة
She has feelings
لديها مشاعرها الخاصة
and a life of her own.
وحياتها الخاصة
She shouldn't have to
وحياتها
become an innocent sacrifice to your schemes.
لا ينبغي أن تذهب ضحية بريئة لمخططاتك
Mao,
ماو
there are no innocent people in this world.
في هذا العالم لا يوجد شخص بريء
The other day, Master asked me
في ذلك اليوم سألني المعلم
whether, in my eyes,
هل أشعر من داخلي
Xiao Wuyi was still a gentleman.
أنك رجلًا نبيلًا؟
Of course I'm not.
بالطبع أنا لست كذلك
Nor do I want to be.
ولا أريد أن أكون
In an age of chaos,
في زمن الفوضى العارمة
gentlemen either fade into obscurity
قد يكون الرجل النبيل مغمورًا
or die with their ambitions buried in the dust.
أو يموت مكسورًا
I will be
أما ما أريده
the one who holds the blade.
هو أن أكون الشخص الذي يمسك السيف
Xiao Wuyi...
شياو وو يي
are you still the same young man
هل ما زلت ذلك الشاب
who once saved me from danger?
الذي أنقذني من المحنة في الماضي؟
This alliance cannot be called off.
لا يمكن إيقاف هذا الزواج
The wedding must proceed as scheduled.
يجب أن يتم حفل الزفاف كما هو مقرر
Fine.
حسنًا
On the wedding day,
في يوم الزفاف
Xie Jiayu and I will leave together.
سأغادر مع شيه جيا يوي
Where could you possibly go?
إلى أين يمكنك الذهاب؟
To the ends of the earth.
إلى أقاصي الأرض
Anywhere.
أي مكان سيفي بالغرض
Then you shouldn't have told me.
إذًا ما كان يجب أن تخبرني
I'm telling you because I still consider you a friend.
هذا لأنني أعتبرك صديقًا
If you want to stop me,
إذا أردت منعي
then just do it.
فلتفعل
You're just as naïve as she is.
أنت ساذج مثلها تمامًا
Mao actually managed to bring this back.
لم أتوقع أن يحضر ماو هذا حقًا
With this,
بهذا
we won't get lost when we run away on the wedding day.
لن أخشى أن أضل طريقي في حفل الزفاف
Mother...
أمي
you already
في الحقيقة
knew all along, didn't you?
أنتِ تعرفين كل شيء، أليس كذلك؟
Mother,
أمي
thank you.
شكرًا لكِ
What are you bowing for out of nowhere?
لماذا تنحنين فجأة هكذا؟
I know
أنا أعرف
that the last time
في المرة السابقة
I had Lejun eat those wild berries to get you to come,
جعلتُ له جيون تأكل الفاكهة البرية لأدعوكِ للمجيء
you had already noticed
في الحقيقة أنتِ
I was hiding among the maids.
اكتشفتِ من البداية أنني مختبئة بين الخادمات
You just chose not to expose me.
لكنكِ لم تكشفي أمري
Later, you even went along with it
وبعد ذلك، سايرتِ الأمر
and took me to Prince Qi's residence.
وأخذتِني إلى قصر أمير تشي
And these past few days, there's no way you wouldn't
وفي هذه الأيام كنت أعبث في القصر بنفسي
have noticed everything I've been secretly preparing in the residence.
ومن المستحيل ألا تعرفي
You simply turned a blind eye
أنتِ فقط تغضين الطرف
because you intended to let me leave.
وتنوين السماح لي بالرحيل
Mother,
أمي
I have failed you.
ابنتك ليست بارة
I've always upset you ever since I was young,
كنت دائمًا أغضبك في الماضي
and now I'm forcing you to make such a difficult choice.
والآن أجبرك على اتخاذ قرار صعب
You're wrong.
أنتِ مخطئة
The daughter I want
الابنة التي أردتها
is not some puppet who only knows how to obey me,
ليست دمية تطيعني في كل شيء
but a young woman
بل فتاة
who truly knows what she wants
تعرف حقًا ما تريد
and what she ought to do.
وتعرف ما يجب عليها فعله
You've been through quite a bit by now.
لقد مررتِ ببعض الأمور
You should understand that the world outside and the Grand Tutor's residence
ويجب أن تعرفي أن العالم الخارجي وقصر المعلم الأكبر
are two entirely different worlds.
عالمان مختلفان
Now that you know how cruel the outside world can be,
لقد عرفتِ قسوة العالم الخارجي
you still intend to leave?
لكنك ما زلتِ تقررين الرحيل
I do.
سأرحل
Then go.
إذًا اذهبي
But remember this:
لكن تذكري
make absolutely sure you're fully prepared.
يجب أن تكوني مستعدة تمامًا
Mother, don't worry.
أمي، اطمئني
Lejun and Mao will both be with me.
له جيون وماو سيكونان معي
Mao said
وماو قال أيضًا
he'll take care of everything.
إنه سيتولى كل شيء
No.
لا
What I mean is
ما أقصده هو
that you yourself must also be fully prepared.
أن عليكِ أنتِ أيضًا أن تكوني مستعدة تمامًا
Remember this:
تذكري
no matter when,
مهما حدث
the one you can truly rely on
الشخص الذي يمكنك الاعتماد عليه حقًا
is never your parents,
ليس والديكِ
your husband,
أو زوجكِ
or your children.
أو أبناؤكِ
It is yourself.
بل أنتِ نفسك
Over here, over here! Hurry up.
من هنا، من هنا، أسرعوا
Make sure you wipe it properly.
امسح بعناية أكبر
Alright!
حسنًا
Xiao Wuyi did indeed risk returning to the capital.
شياو وو يي خاطر بالعودة إلى العاصمة
There are at most 100 household guards inside Jingan Mansion,
يوجد في قصر أمير جينغآن مئة جندي على الأكثر
and everything outside the city remains normal as well.
وخارج المدينة كل شيء كالمعتاد
The Beifu Army is still stationed at the border.
جيش الشمال لا يزال على الحدود
As for the border garrison— he wouldn't dare make any rash move.
مع وجود حامية على الحدود لن يجرؤ على التصرف بتهور
A bride-stealing?
خطف العروس
It's nothing more than an attempt
ليس إلا لمنع
to stop me from securing the support of the noble clans.
حصولي على دعم العائلات الأرستقراطية
The Beifu Army suffered heavy losses at Jiuzhang Plain.
تكبد جيش الشمال خسائر فادحة في سهل جيوتشانغ
We must not wait for the border forces to regroup before we act.
لا يمكننا الانتظار حتى تستعيد حامية الحدود عافيتها قبل أن نتحرك
[Prince Qi's Mansion]
[قصر أمير تشي]
Father.
أبي
Mother.
أمي
♪ A dying memory glimmers low ♪
♪ أتأمل ذكرىً غارقةً في الخفوت والانطفاء ♪
Father.
أبي
♪ You appear, but I can't hold you so ♪
♪ تظهر أمامي، لكنني لا أستطيع بلوغك ♪
I prepared a gift for you.
لقد أعددت لك هدية
♪ Time itself comes to a sudden halt ♪
♪ وفجأة تتوقف لحظة الزمن ♪
♪ So desolate ♪
♪ يا له من شعور بالوحدة الشديدة ♪
It's for massaging your shoulders.
هذا لتدليك الكتفين
Look,
انظر
♪ I traded obsession for this loss ♪
♪ خسارةٌ جلبها الإصرار المتشبث ♪
Just like this.
هكذا
♪ If I could lay my heart bare and cross ♪
♪ لو استطعتُ أن أشقّ هذا القلب ♪
♪ Would you once more have pity on me ♪
♪ فهل كنتَ سترأف بي مرةً أخرى؟ ♪
♪ If the heavens should change and fate tear me apart ♪
♪ ولو تغيّرت السماء فجأةً ومزّقني القدر إربًا ♪
I understand
فهمت
♪ Yet still cannot undo one beat of my heart's art ♪
♪ لكن ذلك لن يُحطّم لحظةً واحدة من الشوق ♪
this is your way of showing filial devotion.
هذا دليل على بر ابنتي جيا يوي
♪ I've traveled so far— the day I find you again ♪
♪ قطعتُ طريقًا شاقًا حتى جاء يوم لقائنا من جديد ♪
♪ I fear you might have forgotten me ♪
♪ أخشى أن تنسى ♪
My dear Yao Yao...
ابنتي جيا يوي
you look so beautiful today.
تبدين جميلة جدًا اليوم
Father,
أبي
if I am no longer by your side in the future,
عندما لا أكن بجانبك في المستقبل
you must take good care of yourself.
يجب أن تعتني بنفسك جيدًا
Silly child,
أيتها الفتاة الحمقاء
why are you crying?
لماذا تبكين؟
I am not crying either.
أبوك لم يبك أيضًا
We'll see each other again someday,
على أي حال، سنلتقي مرة أخرى في المستقبل
won't we?
أليس كذلك؟
It's my fault
أنا من أسأت إليكِ
for letting you be burdened by the Xie family.
وجعلك تتحملين عبء عائلة شيه
If you hadn't been my daughter,
لو لم تكوني ابنتي
your life
لكنتِ عشتِ حياتك
would have been far freer.
بحرية أكبر
Please don't say that, Father.
أبي، لا تقل هذا
Being born your daughter
كوني ابنة عائلة شيه
has made me very happy.
يجعلني سعيدة جدًا
Mother.
أمي
The auspicious hour has arrived.
!لقد حان الوقت الميمون
Young Master Xiao,
ولي العهد شياو
it's been a long time.
لم نلتقِ منذ وقت طويل
When have I ever met you?
متى رأيتك من قبل؟
Fine.
حسنًا
It doesn't matter if you don't remember me.
لا يهم إن كنت لا تتذكرني
After tonight,
من بعد الليلة
I'll make sure you remember me deeply,
سوف أجعلك تتذكر هذه اللحظة
for the rest of your life.
لن تنسى هذا اليوم مهما حييت
I look forward to it.
سننتظر ونرى
Alright, alright.
حسنًا، حسنًا
Don't say things like that in public.
لا تقولي مثل هذا الكلام أمام الجميع
Off you go now—
أسرعا بالذهاب
don't miss the auspicious hour.
لا تؤخرا الوقت الميمون
Xiao Wuyi,
شياو وو يي
a daughter of the Xie family is not so easily won.
الزواج من ابنة عائلة شيه ليس سهلًا
You—get down here.
أنت، انزل
It's not straight.
لقد انحرف
Xiao Wuyi, let go of me!
شياو وو يي، اتركني
Xiao Wuyi,
شياو وو يي
let go of me!
اتركني
Xiao Wuyi, let go of me!
شياو وو يي، اتركني
Xiao Wuyi,
شياو وو يي
let go!
اتركني
Lord Li, Madam Li.
السيد لي وسيدته
-Congratulations.
تهانينا، تهانينا
Mr. Zhang, please come in.
أخي تشانغ، تفضل بالدخول
Xiao Wuyi, let go of me!
شياو وو يي، اتركني
You jerk! You villain!
أيها الوغد، أيها الرجل السيء
Put me down!
أنزلني
Xiao Wuyi, let go of me!
شياو وو يي، اتركني
Let go of me! Put me down!
اتركني، أنزلني
Xiao Wuyi,
شياو وو يي
put me down!
أنزلني
Xiao Wuyi, put me down.
شياو وو يي، أنزلني
Xiao Wuyi, you...
شياو وو يي، أنت
Yan Yue.
يان يوه
-Yes. -Take her to the bridal chamber.
نعم - خذها إلى غرفة العرس -
Don't give her any food
لا تعطوها أي طعام
or water.
ولا أي شراب
Xiao Wuyi, just you wait.
شياو وو يي، انتظر وسوف ترى
Tonight, I'll make you regret this for the rest of your life.
الليلة، سأجعلك تندم طوال حياتك
Is this meant to be a show of force against the Xie family?
هل تريدون توجيه إنذار لعائلة شيه؟
More than that.
ليس فقط ضد عائلة شيه
The one being humiliated is Grand Tutor Xie himself.
بل وإهانة للمعلم الأكبر شيه
Take good care of my secondary consort.
اعتنوا جيدًا بمحظيتكم
I don't want to hear a single sound from her tonight.
لا أريد أن أسمع صوتها مجددًا هذه الليلة
Yes.
!أمرك
Your Highness, the wedding rites haven't been completed yet.
يا ولي العهد، المراسم لم تكتمل بعد
Since you're all here,
بما أنكم جميعًا هنا
drink with me tonight until we're completely drunk and no one leaves sober.
فلتشربوا معي الليلة لن نغادر حتى نكتفي من الشراب
None of you are leaving.
لا يفكر أحد منكم في المغادرة
Wuyi,
أخي الثاني
tonight is the wedding bestowed by the Empress Dowager.
الليلة هي ليلة الزفاف التي أمرت بها الإمبراطورة الأم
-Let's go. -Don't—
هيا - لا تفعل -
Come on, let's drink!
لنشرب
Your Highness,
سموك
most of the court officials invited to the wedding banquet have already arrived.
لقد وصل معظم رجال البلاط المدعوين إلى مأدبة الزفاف
The remaining senior ministers are also on their way.
كما أن عددًا من كبار الوزراء في طريقهم أيضًا
Proceed according to plan.
نفذوا الخطة
My life and death, my honor and disgrace— all depend on tonight.
حياتي ومماتي، وعزتي وذلي، سيتحددان الليلة
Yes.
!أمرك
My Lady,
سيدتي
Xiao Wuyi is going too far.
شياو وو يي هذا متسلط للغاية
He actually had you carried all the way back to the mansion—
لقد حملك قسرًا طوال الطريق إلى القصر
and on top of that…
وفوق ذلك
on your wedding night,
في ليلة الزفاف
he's drinking and making merry with dancing girls.
يشرب ويمرح مع الراقصات
It doesn't matter.
لا بأس
In any case, the one who will be utterly humiliated tonight is him.
على أي حال، هو من سيتعرض للإحراج الأكبر الليلة
One at the door,
واحد عند الباب
and two outside the window.
واثنان خارج النافذة
Even the numbers line up exactly with the map.
حتى العدد يطابق ما هو على الخريطة
Heaven is helping me!
إنها حقًا مساعدة من السماء
Are you all ready?
هل أنتم جميعًا مستعدون؟
A top-grade sleeping draught.
مسحوق منوم بتركيبة فائقة
Is anyone outside?
هل من أحد في الخارج؟
My Lady is in trouble—
سيدتي ليست على ما يرام
someone help!
!النجدة
Hurry! Come in, come in!
ادخلوا بسرعة، ادخلوا بسرعة
Let's go.
هيا
How come there isn't a single soul
قصر أمير جينغآن
in this entire Jingan Mansion?
كيف لا يوجد فيه أي شخص؟
Ugh… it stinks.
!يا لها من رائحة كريهة
No, no—
لا، ليس من هنا
this is the outhouse.
هذا هو المرحاض
The main gate is to the east...
بوابة الفناء تتجه شرقًا
The kitchen's over there.
المطبخ في ذلك الاتجاه
Hurry, move!
لنتحرك بسرعة
Don't block the entrance—
لا تقفن عند المدخل
we're serving food!
إننا نقدم الطعام
Douzi, take the slop out!
شياو دو تسي، اسكب ماء الغسيل
Alright!
حسنًا
Let's go.
هيا
What are you all doing here?
ما الذي أتى بكن إلى هنا؟
How was it?
ما رأيك؟
Did we seem real enough?
بدا تمثيلنا حقيقيًا، أليس كذلك؟
He was pretending too?
هو أيضًا كان يتظاهر
He wasn't.  You still need someone real in the mix, don't you?
هو ليس كذلك، يجب أن يكون هناك شخص حقيقي
Your Highness, they've already left.
يا ولي العهد، لقد غادرن
Which route?
من أي طريق؟
As expected, the bride chose the back kitchen path.
العروس اختارت المطبخ الخلفي كما هو متوقع
She just took several wrong turns along the way.
لكنها أخطأت الطريق عدة مرات
This is the hairpin she dropped.
هذا دبوس شعرها اللؤلؤي الذي أسقطته
Even with a map, she can't find her way.
حتى مع وجود خريطة، لا تعرف كيف تهرب
She is so stupid.
!يا لها من غبية حقًا
It's bad—
!مصيبة
the bride has escaped!
لقد هربت العروس
What did you say?
ماذا تقولين؟
In my mansion, from the guards to the gardeners,
في قصري يوجد جنود تابعون للقصر وبستانيون
groundskeepers, and stablehands—
ومنسقو زهور وسائسو خيل
every one of them knows martial arts.
لا يوجد أحد منهم لا يجيد فنون القتال
The moment she steps out of the courtyard gate,
بمجرد أن تخرج من بوابة الفناء
she will be detected.
سيتم اكتشاف أمرها
If you plan to escape,
إذا أردتم الهرب
you would need my help.
فلا سبيل لك إلا بمساعدتي
This is the map of Jingan Mansion.
هذه خريطة قصر أمير جينغآن
Xie Jiayu will need it if she tries to escape the wedding.
ستحتاجها شيه جيا يوي عندما تهرب من الزواج
But this wedding must proceed as scheduled.
لكن يجب أن يقام هذا الزفاف كما هو مقرر
because this is the day I have chosen for Prince Changsha
لأن هذا هو اليوم الذي اخترته لإجبار أمير تشانغشا
to force the abdication.
على التنازل عن العرش
All guards of Jingan Mansion, heed my order.
يا حراس قصر أمير جينغآن استمعوا لأمري
-Yes!
نعم
Search the entire city for Xie Jiayu!
ابحثوا في جميع أنحاء المدينة عن شيه جيا يوي
Yes, Your Highness.
!أمرك
-Split up and search. -Make way.
تفرقوا للبحث - أفسحوا الطريق -
-Move! -Make way!
أفسحوا الطريق، أفسحوا الطريق
What's going on?
ما الذي حدث؟
Lady Xie has fled the wedding.
السيدة شيه هربت من الزواج
Xiao Wuyi has ordered his guards to search the entire city.
شياو وو يي أمر حراسه بالبحث عنها في كل أنحاء المدينة
This Lady Xie
هذه السيدة شيه
is always full of surprises.
دائمًا تأتي بما لا يخطر على البال
Your Highness, Jingan Mansion is now lightly guarded.
يا صاحب السمو، قصر أمير جينغآن فارغ الآن
Should we strike immediately?
ألا يجب أن نتحرك على الفور؟
A heaven-sent opportunity.
!إنها فرصة من السماء
Issue the order inside and outside the capital—
انقلوا أمري داخل العاصمة وخارجها
begin the uprising at once.
لبدء التمرد فورًا
Yes.
!أمرك
Attack!
!هجوم
Take Mother and leave, quickly!
خذي أمي واذهبي بسرعة
Yao, be careful!
شياو ياو، كن حذرًا
Who are you?
من أنتم؟
How dare you act so recklessly in Jingan Mansion!
كيف تجرؤون على إثارة الفوضى في قصر أمير جينغآن؟
Yuanji!
يوان جي
Today,
اليوم
I shall cleanse His Majesty's side of traitors
سأُطهر حاشية جلالته
and seize the rebels.
وأقبض على الخائن
Among all the ministers in this courtyard,
هؤلاء الوزراء في الساحة
which one is a rebel?
من منهم هو الخائن؟
Xiao Wuyi.
شياو وو يي
He brought troops back to the capital without imperial decree,
لقد عاد إلى العاصمة بقواته دون مرسوم
slaughtered court officials,
وقتل وزراء البلاط عشوائيًا
and harbors treasonous ambitions.
نواياه خبيثة
His crimes deserve death.
وجريمته تستحق الإعدام
Tonight,
الليلة
who among you dare stand as his accomplice?
من هو شريكه؟
It seems
يبدو
the only rebel here is Xiao Wuyi himself.
أنه لا يوجد خائن سوى شياو وو يي
Your Highness, we've just received word—
يا صاحب السمو، وردت أنباء للتو
the palace gates have been breached.
أن أبواب القصر قد سقطت
Surround Jingan Mansion.
حاصروا قصر أمير جينغآن
With Xiao Wuyi's family
عائلة شياو وو يي
and these court officials
وهؤلاء الوزراء
here,
ما داموا هنا
he won't be able to escape.
فلن يتمكن شياو وو يي من الهرب
The rest of you follow me into the palace
البقية، اتبعوني إلى القصر
to meet the Empress Dowager.
لنحيي الإمبراطورة الأرملة
Yes.
!أمرك
Hurry! Move!
أسرعا، أسرعا، أسرعا
Search thoroughly—
ابحثوا في كل مكان جيدًا
leave no alley unchecked.
لا تتركوا أي زقاق دون تفتيش
Yes.
!أمرك
Search!
ابحثوا
Your Highness,
يا ولي العهد
Xie Jiayu's trail has been found at Wuling Gate.
تم رصد شيه جيا يوي عند بوابة وو لينغ
Guard the city gate.
أحكموا إغلاق بوابات المدينة
I want her dead,
أريدها ميتة
not alive.
لا أريدها حية
Yes.
!أمرك -
Oh, Xiao Wuyi...
شياو وو يي، يا شياو وو يي
You're certainly ruthless—
أنت قاسٍ جدًا
but your eyesight isn't all that great.
لكن بصرك ليس جيدًا
My Lady, it's just that you're blessed by the True Deity.
سيدتي، أنتِ تحظين بحماية الآلهة بحق
Even the heavens can't stand by
حتى السماء لم تعد تحتمل رؤية هذا الظلم
and have chosen to help you.
لذا أرادت مساعدتك
Let's go quickly,
هيا بنا نسرع
or Mao will be getting anxious.
وإلا سينتظر ماو وهو قلق
Let's go.
هيا، هيا، هيا
Master?
يا معلم
His Majesty is gravely ill
جلالة الإمبراطور مريض جدًا
and has summoned Prince Qi to enter the palace at once and attend upon him.
أمر أمير تشي بدخول القصر فورًا لرعايته
I can't go to the palace.
لا يمكنني دخول القصر
I need to find Yao Yao.
أريد أن أبحث عن جيا يوي
Guards, escort Prince Qi to the palace.
يا حراس، رافقوا أمير تشي إلى القصر
Lejun!
له جيون
Brother!
أخي
Your Highness.
يا صاحب السمو
Are all our men assembled?
هل وصل الجميع؟
Tonight, we suddenly lost all contact
لقد فقدنا اللية فجأة
with forces outside the capital.
التواصل بخارج العاصمة
Several units have been sent out, but none have reported back.
أرسلنا عدة فرق ولم يعد أي منها
Lost contact?
فقدنا التواصل
We won't wait any longer!
لن ننتظر أكثر
Victory or defeat, honor or disgrace— it all comes down to tonight.
النجاح أو الفشل، والمجد أو العار، كلّها تتحدد هذه الليلة
Enter the palace now. Kill the Emperor and Empress Dowager!
ادخلوا القصر واقتلوا الإمبراطور والإمبراطورة الأرملة
Yes!
!أمرك
-Kill!
اقتلوا، اقتلوا، اقتلوا
Your Highness,
يا صاحب السمو
His Majesty is not in the main hall.
جلالته ليس في القاعة
Not there?
ليس هنا؟
That sickly man can't even get out of bed—
هذا المعتل لا يستطيع حتى مغادرة سريره
where could he possibly go?
إلى أين يمكن أن يذهب؟
Find him!
ابحثوا عنه
Yes.
!أمرك
[Xuanzheng Hall]
[قصر شيوان تشنغ]
Tell me—
تكلمي
where have you hidden that sickly emperor?
أين خبأتِ ذلك المعتل؟
My son is the true Son of Heaven.
ابني هو الإمبراطور الموعود
He is protected by the True Deity.
وهو تحت حماية الآلهة
You think you can find him so easily?
كيف لي أن أسمح لك بالعثور عليه؟
Don't think I'm unaware.
لا تظني أنني لا أعرف
Had you not forged the imperial edict
في ذلك العام، لولا تزويرك للمرسوم الإمبراطوري
and poisoned the late emperor,
وتسميم الإمبراطور الراحل
your son would never have become emperor.
لما كان الدور ليصل إلى ابنك ليصبح إمبراطورًا
But Heaven sees all.
لكن لحسن الحظ، السماء عادلة
Ever since he ascended the throne,
منذ أن أصبح إمبراطورًا
he's been bedridden with illness.
وهو طريح الفراش
This is his retribution.
هذا هو الجزاء
How insolent!
!وقاحة
Utter nonsense!
!هذا هراء محض
My son is the true Son of Heaven!
ابني هو الإمبراطور الموعود
Then let's see tonight
إذًا لنرَ هذه الليلة
who truly holds Heaven's Mandate.
في صف من سيقف القدر
Guards—
...هيا
Why didn't you attend my wedding tonight?
لماذا لم تأتِ الليلة لتشرب شراب زفافي؟
Xiao Wuyi, didn't you go find Xie...
...شياو وو يي، ألم تذهب للبحث عن شيه
It doesn't matter.
لا بأس
Tonight, my 20,000 troops have already taken control of the capital.
قواتي البالغ عددها عشرون ألفًا قد سيطرت بالفعل على العاصمة الليلة
Those who follow me will prosper; those who oppose me will perish.
من يطيعني يزدهر، ومن يعصيني يهلك.
Kill Xiao Wuyi!
اقتلوا شياو وو يي
What are you afraid of?
مم تخافون؟
Whoever kills Xiao Wuyi shall be granted a fief of ten thousand households!
من يقتل شياو وو يي يُكافأ بإقطاع عشرة آلاف أسرة
You mean those forces outside the capital?
هل تقصد أولئك الذين خارج المدينة؟
I've already wiped them out.
لقد قتلتهم
What do you mean?
ماذا تقصد؟
Kneel!
اركعوا
-Spare us, Your Highness! -Please spare us!
يا ولي العهد، ارحمني، يا ولي العهد
Where are they?
أين هم؟
Where are the others?
أين البقية؟
-Please spare us, Your Highness! -Please spare us!
يا ولي العهد، ارحمني -
No… I won't lose.
لا، لن أخسر
I absolutely will not lose.
مستحيل أن أخسر
I still have Jingan Mansion,
لا يزال لديّ قصر أمير جينغآن
all those ministers,
والعديد من الأمراء والوزراء
and your entire family.  If you dare—
...وعائلتك بأكملها، إذا تجرأت
His Highness has given the order—
أمر من الأمير
kill!
!اقتلوهم
Yes.
!أمرك
Who dares take another step forward?
من يجرؤ على التقدم؟
I am the Princess of Jingan Mansion,
أنا زوجة ولي عهد قصر أمير جينغآن
the Empress Dowager's own niece.
وابنة أخ الإمبراطورة الأرملة الحالية
Let's see who dares lay a hand on me today!
لأرَ من يجرؤ على لمسي اليوم
Did you think I didn't know
هل تظن أنني لا أعرف
you would move against Jingan Mansion?
أنك ستستهدف قصر أمير جينغآن؟
How dare a useless drunkard from pleasure-filled Jiankang City like you
حثالة عديمو الفائدة غارقون في ملذات مدينة جيانكانغ
play war games with me?
كيف يجرؤون على استخدام حيل الحرب ضدي؟
[Xiao Ju, Prince Jing'an]
[أمير جينغآن، شياو جيوي]
Father.
أبي الأمير
Are you alright?
أنتم بخير
I'm fine.
لا بأس
Your Highness.
سيدي الأمير
My Lady.
سيدتي
Lady Rui, have you not been in the mansion these past few days?
السيدة روي، لم تكوني في القصر هذه الأيام
Due to urgent military matters,
الوضع العسكري طارئ
Wuyi asked her to guide me outside the capital.
وو يي طلب منها أن ترشدني خارج المدينة
Yao.
شياو ياو
It's alright.
لا تقلقي
All of you, listen well!
اسمعوا جميعًا
Prince Changsha has attempted a palace coup.
أمير تشانغشا تمرد ليجبر الإمبراطور على التنازل عن العرش
The Beifu Army has marched thousands of miles to suppress the rebellion.
جنود جيش الشمال قطعوا آلاف الأميال لإخماد التمرد
At this very moment,
في هذه اللحظة
my son Xiao Wuyi has already captured Prince Changsha alive within the palace.
ابني شياو وو يي قد أسر أمير تشانغشا حيًا في القصر
Surrender immediately!
استسلموا جميعًا فورًا
or you will all be slain without mercy.
وإلا، فسيتم قتلكم بلا رحمة
The Beifu Army is back…
جيش الشمال قد عاد
Is this truly suppressing a rebellion… or starting one?
هل هذا إخماد للتمرد أم تمرد بحد ذاته؟
I can't accept this!
لا أقبل بهذا
I'm unwilling to keep being trampled
لا أقبل أن يبقيني هذا الإمبراطور عديم الفائدة
under the feet of that useless emperor.
تحت قدميه طوال الوقت
Do you regret it?
هل أنت نادم؟
Regret?
نادم؟
I have never felt so alive and satisfied.
لم أشعر بالرضا قط كما شعرت الليلة
Xiao Wuyi, do you think killing me
شياو وو يي، هل تظن أنك بقتلي
will avenge the Beifu Army who died in vain?
تستطيع الثأر لجنود جيش الشمال الذين ماتوا ظلمًا؟
Don't think you're any different from me—
لا تظن أنك مختلف عني
don't you also want to kill that useless emperor
ألا تريد قتل هذا الإمبراطور عديم الفائدة
and take his place in this Xianyang Hall?
والسكن في قصر شيانيانغ؟
Aunt…
يا عمة
Your Majesty…
أيتها الإمبراطورة الأرملة
Xiao Wuyi will kill you both sooner or later.
شياو وو يي سيقتلكم بالتأكيد
Perhaps even tonight.
ربما في هذه الليلة
How foolish and self-deceived.
!يا لك من أحمق لا تعي حماقتك
You don't even know who is the piece
لا تعرف حتى من هو البيدق الليلة
and who is the player on this board.
ومن هو اللاعب
I originally believed Prince Changsha
كنت أظن في الأصل أن أمير تشانغشا
had secretly colluded with Wonderful Master,
تآمر سرًا مع صاحبة اليد البارعة
bribing the Armory Director in my army
ورشا قائد مستودع الأسلحة
to purchase a batch of defective repeating crossbows.
لشراء دفعة من الأقواس الآلية الرديئة للجيش
But it turned out Wonderful Master
لكن اتضح أن صاحبة اليد البارعة
didn't even know you.
لا تعرفك على الإطلاق
The real mastermind behind the purchase
في الحقيقة، المشتري الحقيقي وراء الكواليس
is the Empress Dowager.
هي الإمبراطورة الأرملة
The one who most wants to see me and Prince Changsha destroy each other…
والشخص الذي يرغب أكثر في أن أتقاتل أنا وأمير تشانغشا حتى الموت
is also the Empress Dowager.
هي الإمبراطورة الأرملة أيضًا
Young Master Xiao, you are indeed perceptive.
ولي العهد شياو ذكي حقًا
The official in charge of military supplies, Treasurer Wei,
مسؤول الأسلحة العسكرية نائب مدير الخزانة وي
is an ally of Prince Changsha.
هو من أتباع أمير تشانغشا
As long as you handed him the design plans,
كل ما كان على الإمبراطورة الأرملة فعله هو إعطاء المخططات لنائب مدير الخزانة وي
he would complete the rest of the scheme with Prince Changsha,
وهو سيكمل الباقي مع أمير تشانغشا
and eliminate both me and the Beifu Army.
لوضعي أنا وجيش الشمال في موقف مميت
Just like tonight—
تمامًا مثل الليلة
Your Majesty neither mobilized troops nor prepared defenses,
لم تحرك الإمبراطورة الأم أي قوات ولم تتخذ أي احتياطات
betting that even though I knew this palace entry was a trap,
أليس هذا لأنك تراهنين على أنني رغم علمي بأن دخول القصر بلا أمر هو فخ
I would still refuse to let Prince Changsha succeed.
لن أسمح لأمير تشانغشا بالنجاح أبدًا؟
So tonight,
لذا
Your Majesty's target
هدف الإمبراطورة الأرملة هذه الليلة
is not only Prince Changsha…
ليس فقط أمير تشانغشا
but me as well.
بل أنا أيضًا
What a perfect invitation into a trap.
يا لها من خطة بارعة لاستدراج العدو إلى الفخ
I always thought
لطالما ظننت
you were nothing more than a useless old woman.
أنكِ مجرد امرأة عجوز لا فائدة منها
I didn't expect this.
لم أتوقع هذا أبدًا
Fine—
حسنًا
I lose this round
في هذه الجولة
without complaint.
خسارتي ليست ظلمًا
Since you already knew tonight was a trap,
بما أنك كنت تعلم أن اليوم فخ
why did you still come?
فلماذا أتيت إلى القصر؟
Because I did not want
لأنني لا أريد
Jiankang to run red with blood tonight.
أن تتحول جيانكانغ الليلة إلى نهر من الدماء
But
لكن
I must demand justice for the 30,000 fallen soldiers
يجب أن أحقق العدالة لثلاثين ألفًا من جنود جيش الشمال
of the Beifu Army.
الذين ماتوا ظلمًا
Brave indeed.
!يا لك من شجاع
I can spare your life.
يمكنني أن أعفو عن حياتك
If you are willing to surrender your military command,
إذا كنت على استعداد لتسليم سلطتك العسكرية
I will grant you immunity.
سأعفو عنك
And if I refuse?
وماذا لو رفضت؟
Empress Dowager,
الإمبراطورة الأرملة
I submitted the roster of our fallen soldiers
لقد قدمتُ قائمة الجنود الذين استشهدوا في المعركة
half a month ago.
وقد مر نصف شهر بالفعل
I wonder if you have read it?
أتساءل إن كنتِ قد اطلعتِ عليها؟
Not yet.
ليس بعد
Shi Yuchun,
شي يوي تشون
46 years old—
ستة وأربعون عامًا
stabbed over 100 times, yet died without kneeling.
مات واقفًا بعد أن تلقى أكثر من مئة طعنة
Xie Han, a veteran of the Beifu Army.
شيه هان، جندي مخضرم من جيش الشمال
He spent his entire life at war,
قاتل طوال حياته
and could have laid down his armor and returned home—
كان بإمكانه أن يتقاعد ويعود إلى دياره
but his homeland had already fallen to Northern Qin.
لكن مسقط رأسه سقط منذ زمن طويل في أيدي مملكة تشين الشمالية
He said he has nowhere else to go
قال إنه لا مأوى له
and wishes to spend the rest of his life in the army.
وأراد أن يموت في الجيش
This time,
هذه المرة
he truly did die—
لقد مات بالفعل
his body trampled into a pulp beneath enemy hooves.
سحقت قوات العدو جثته حتى تحولت إلى أشلاء
Zhang Ji, my most trusted deputy.
تشانغ جي، أفضل مساعد لي
He personally set fire to the vine-armored grain depot
أشعل النار بنفسه في مستودع حبوب قوات دروع الرَّتان
and perished together with the enemy.
وفي النهاية مات مع العدو
Does Your Majesty know any of this?
هل تعرفين كل هذا يا صاحبة السمو؟
Do you, sitting here in Jiankang, even care?
هل اهتممتِ يومًا وأنتِ في العاصمة جيانكانغ؟
That is why I will not surrender my command—
لذلك، لن أسلم السلطة العسكرية
because apart from me,
...لأنه باستثنائي
no one else cares about their lives.
لا أحد يهتم بحياتهم
Xiao Wuyi,
شياو وو يي
the Beifu Army entered the capital without an imperial decree.
دخل جيش الشمال العاصمة دون مرسوم إمبراطوري
Are you trying to rebel?
هل تنوي التمرد؟
But you will end up returning to Jiankang without the Emperor's decree.
لكنك عدت إلى جيانكانغ دون مرسوم من جلالة الإمبراطور
What about mobilizing troops?
ماذا عن تحريك القوات؟
Prince Changsha seeks rebellion—
أمير تشانغشا يخطط للتمرد
what about you?
ماذا عنك؟
Your Majesty,
صاحبة السمو الإمبراطورة الأرملة
all I want is peace across the realm.
كل ما أريده هو السلام في العالم
Is Your Majesty willing to grant that?
هل ستمنحينني إياه؟
Have you ever heard the war drums
هل سمعتِ من قبل يا صاحبة السمو
of the Beifu Army?
صوت طبول حرب جيش الشمال؟
One hundred thousand Beifu troops
مئة ألف جندي من جيش الشمال
are just outside the city now.
خارج أسوار المدينة مباشرة